How would you like to be better than you are?
ما رأيك لو تصبح أفضل مما أنت عليه؟
Suppose I said
لنفترض أنني قلت
that, with just a few changes in your genes,
بأنه مع بعض التعديلات البسيطة في جيناتك
you could get a better memory --
ستصبح بذاكرة أفضل
more precise,
أكثر تحديداً
more accurate and quicker.
أكثر دقة وأسرع
Or maybe you'd like to be more fit, stronger,
أو ربما ترغب في أن تصبح ذو بنية أفضل، أقوى
with more stamina.
مع المزيد من طاقة التحمل
Would you like to be more attractive and self-confident?
هل ترغب في أن تصبح أكثر جاذبية وثقة بالنفس؟
How about living longer with good health?
ماذا عن عمر أطول بصحة جيدة؟
Or perhaps you're one of those
أو ربما أنت أحد هؤلاء
who's always yearned for more creativity.
الذي يطمح دائماً للمزيد من الابداع
Which one would you like the most?
ماذا تفضل أن تختار؟
Which would you like, if you could have just one?
ماذا تختار لو كان بامكانك الحصول على واحدة فقط
(Audience Member: Creativity.)
(أحد الحضور: الابداع)
Creativity.
الابداع.
How many people would choose creativity?
كم شخصاً سيختار الابداع؟
Raise your hands. Let me see.
ارفعوا أيديكم. دعوني أرى.
A few. Probably about as many as there are creative people here.
القليل. على أغلب بنفس عدد الأشخاص المبدعين هنا.
(Laughter) That's very good.
هذا جيد جداً.
How many would opt for memory?
كم شخصاً يختار الذاكرة؟
Quite a few more.
أكثر بقليل
How about fitness?
ماذا عن لياقة البدن؟
A few less.
أقل بقليل
What about longevity?
ماذا عن طول العمر؟
Ah, the majority. That makes me feel very good as a doctor.
آه، الغالبية. هذا يسعدني كطبيب.
If you could have any one of these,
إذا كان بمقدورك الحصول على أي واحدة من هولاء
it would be a very different world.
سيصبح عالماً مختلفاً جداً.
Is it just imaginary?
هل هذا مجرد تخيلات؟
Or, is it, perhaps, possible?
أم أن هذا ممكن؟
Evolution has been a perennial topic
أصبحت نظرية التطور موضوعاً دائماً
here at the TED Conference,
هنا في مؤتمر TED,
but I want to give you today
لكنني أريد أن أقدم لكم اليوم
one doctor's take on the subject.
رأي أحد الأطباء في هذا الموضوع.
The great 20th-century geneticist,
أعظم عالم وراثة في القرن العشرين,
T.G. Dobzhansky,
تي. جي. دوبجيهانسكيو,
who was also a communicant
وهو أيضا المناول
in the Russian Orthodox Church,
في الكنيسة الأرثوذكسية الروسية,
once wrote an essay that he titled
كتب في مرة مقالاً بعنوان
"Nothing in Biology Makes Sense
"لا شيء منطقي في علم الأحياء
Except in the Light of Evolution."
إلا في ضوء نظرية التطور".
Now if you are one of those
الآن إذا كنت واحداً
who does not accept the evidence for biological evolution,
ممن لا يقبلون الدليل في نظرية التطور الأحيائي
this would be a very good time to turn off your hearing aid,
سيكون هذا الوقت المناسب جداً لإطفاء سماعتك
take out your personal communications device --
ونزع جهاز الارسال الخاص --
I give you permission --
أنا أعطيك الإذن --
and perhaps take another look at Kathryn Schultz's book on being wrong,
أو ربما تأخذ وجة نظر أخرى بأن كتاب كاثرين شولتز خاطيء
because nothing in the rest of this talk
لأنه لا شيء في باقي هذه المحاضرة
is going to make any sense whatsoever to you.
سيكون منطقياً بالنسبة لك أياً يكون.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But if you do accept
لكن إذا قبلت
biological evolution,
بنظرية تطور العضوي
consider this:
انظر لهذا:
is it just about the past,
هل يتعلق الأمر بالماضي فقط,
or is it about the future?
أم أنه يتعلق بالمستقبل فقط؟
Does it apply to others,
هل تنطبق على الآخرين,
or does it apply to us?
أم تنطبق علينا؟
This is another look at the tree of life.
هذه نظرة أخرى لشجرة الحياة.
In this picture,
في هذه الصورة,
I've put a bush with a center branching out in all directions,
لقد وضعت شجيرة يتفرع فيها المركز إلى الخارج في كل الاتجاهات,
because if you look at the edges
لأنك إذا نظرت إلى أطراف
of the tree of life,
شجرة الحياة,
every existing species
كل الأجناس الموجودة
at the tips of those branches
على أطراف هذه الفروع
has succeeded in evolutionary terms:
قد نجحت بمصطلحات نظرية التطور:
it has survived;
قد نجت؛
it has demonstrated a fitness
قد أبدت تلائماً
to its environment.
مع بيئتها.
The human part of this branch,
الجزء البشري في هذا الفرع
way out on one end,
بعيداً جداً في إحدى النهايات,
is, of course, the one that we are most interested in.
هو بالتأكيد أكثر جزء نهتم به.
We branch off of a common ancestor
لقد تفرعنا من سلف "جد" مشترك
to modern chimpanzees
إلى الشمبانزي الحديث
about six or eight million years ago.
قبل ستة أو ثمانية ملايين سنة مضت.
In the interval,
خلال هذه المدة,
there have been perhaps 20 or 25
ربما كان هنالك 20 أو 25
different species of hominids.
أجناس مختلفة شبيه بالإنسان
Some have come and gone.
البعض أتى وذهب.
We have been here for about 130,000 years.
إننا هنا منذ 130,000 سنة تقريبا.
It may seem like we're quite remote
قد يبدو أننا بعيدون تماماً
from other parts of this tree of life,
عن الأجزاء الأخرى في شجرة الحياة هذه,
but actually, for the most part,
لكن في الواقع, في الجزء الأكبر,
the basic machinery of our cells
الآلية الأساسية في خلايانا,
is pretty much the same.
متشابهة إلى حد بعيد.
Do you realize that we can take advantage
هل تدرك بأنه بمقدورنا الاستفادة
and commandeer the machinery of a common bacterium
وتوظيف آلية نوع من البكريا الشائعة
to produce the protein of human insulin
لإنتاج بروتين الأنسولين البشري
used to treat diabetics?
المستخدم لعلاج مرض السكري؟
This is not like human insulin;
هذا ليس مثل الإنسولين البشري؛
this is the same protein
إنه نفس البروتين
that is chemically indistinguishable
الذي لا يمكن تميزه كيمائياً
from what comes out of your pancreas.
عن الذي تفرزه البنكرياس لديك.
And speaking of bacteria,
وبالحديث عن البكتيريا,
do you realize that each of us carries in our gut
هل تدرك أن كل واحد منا يحمل في أمعائنا
more bacteria
بكتيريا
than there are cells in the rest of our body?
أكثر من الخلايا في باقي جسمنا؟
Maybe 10 times more.
ربما أكثر بعشرة مرات,
I mean think of it,
أقصد فكر بذلك,
when Antonio Damasio asks about your self-image,
عندما يسأل من أنطونيو داماسيو عن صورة ذاتك,
do you think about the bacteria?
هل تفكر في البكتيريا؟
Our gut is a wonderfully hospitable environment
أمعاءنا هي بيئة مستضيفة رائعة
for those bacteria.
لهذه البكتيريا.
It's warm, it's dark, it's moist,
إنها دافئة، إنها مظلمة، إنها رطبة,
it's very cozy.
إنها مريحة للغاية.
And you're going to provide all the nutrition that they could possibly want
وأنت ستقدم كل التغذية التي قد تحتاج إليها
with no effort on their part.
بدون جهد لإجزاءها
It's really like an Easy Street for bacteria,
إنها بالفعل الطريق السهل للبكتيريا,
with the occasional interruption
مع انقطاع بين الحين والآخر
of the unintended forced rush to the exit.
للدفقات غير المقصودة التي تجبرها على الخروج.
But otherwise,
لكن فيما عدا ذلك,
you are a wonderful environment for those bacteria,
أنت بيئة رائعة لهذه البكتيريا,
just as they are essential to your life.
تماما كما هي أساسية لحياتك.
They help in the digestion of essential nutrients,
إنها تساعد في هضم الغذاء الأساسي.
and they protect you against certain diseases.
وتساعد في الحماية من بعض الأمراض.
But what will come in the future?
لكن ما هو القادم في المستقبل؟
Are we at some kind of evolutionary equipoise
هل نحن في نوع ما من التوازن التطوري
as a species?
كأجناس؟
Or, are we destined
أم هل نحن متجهون
to become something different --
لكي نصبح شيئاً مختلفاً --
something, perhaps, even better adapted
شيئاً ربما أكثر تلائماً
to the environment?
مع البيئة؟
Now let's take a step back in time
الآن دعونا نعود خطوة للوراء في الزمن
to the Big Bang, 14 billion years ago --
إلى الإنفجار الكبير, قبل 14 بليون سنة --
the Earth, the solar system,
الأرض، المجموعة الشمسية,
about four and a half billion years --
حوالي أربعة بلايين سنة ونصف
the first signs of proto-life,
أول إشارات لحياة بروتينية,
maybe three to four billion years ago on Earth --
ربما قبل ثلاثة أو أربع بلايين سنة على الأرض --
the first multi-celled organisms,
أول كائن حي متعدد الخلايا
perhaps as much
ربما كانت تقريبا
as 800 or a billion years ago --
قبل 800 أو بليون عام مضت
and then the human species,
وعندها الجنس البشري
finally emerging
نشأ أخيراً
in the last 130,000 years.
في 130,000 سنة الأخيرة
In this vast unfinished symphony of the universe,
في هذه السيموفونية الشاسعة غير المكتملة للكون
life on Earth is like a brief measure;
الحياة على الأرض هي لحن صغير
the animal kingdom,
الممكلة الحيوانية،
like a single measure;
هي لحن واحد
and human life,
والحياة الإنسانية
a small grace note.
هي نوتة رخيمة صغيرة
That was us.
نحن مثل هذه
That also constitutes the entertainment portion of this talk,
كما أنها تعزز القسم الترفيهي في هذه المحاضرة
so I hope you enjoyed it.
لذا آمل أن تستمتعوا بها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now when I was a freshman in college,
عندما كنت طالباً في السنة الأولى في الجامعة
I took my first biology class.
وأخذت أول درس في علم الأحياء
I was fascinated
لقد فتنت
by the elegance and beauty of biology.
بأناقة وجمال علم الأحياء
I became enamored of the power of evolution,
أصحبت مفتوناً بقوة التطور
and I realized something very fundamental:
ولاحظت أيضاً أمراً أساسياً للغاية
in most of the existence of life
في غالبة أنماط الحياة الحالية
in single-celled organisms,
في كائنات وحيدة الخلية،
each cell simply divides,
كل خلية تنقسم ببساطة
and all of the genetic energy of that cell
وكل الطاقة الجينية في تلك الخلية
is carried on in both daughter cells.
يتم حملها في كلتا الخليتين الأبناء.
But at the time multi-celled organisms come online,
لكن عندما يكون هنالك كائن متعدد الخلايا،
things start to change.
تبدأ الأمور بالتغير.
Sexual reproduction enters the picture.
يتدخل التكاثر الجنسي في الصورة.
And very importantly,
وأكثر أهمية من ذلك،
with the introduction of sexual reproduction
مع دخول التكاثر الجنسي
that passes on the genome,
الذي يقوم بتمرير الجينات،
the rest of the body
فإن باقي الجسد
becomes expendable.
يصبح مستهلكاً.
In fact, you could say
في الحقيقة، يمكنك القول
that the inevitability of the death of our bodies
بأن حتمية موت أجسادنا
enters in evolutionary time
تدخل في الزمن التطوري
at the same moment
في نفس اللحظة
as sexual reproduction.
عند دخول التكاثر الجنسي
Now I have to confess,
الآن علي أن أعترف،
when I was a college undergraduate,
عندما كنت طالباً في الجامعة،
I thought, okay, sex/death, sex/death, death for sex --
قلت لنفسي ، حسناً، الجنس/الموت ـ الجنس/الموت ، الموت لأجل الجنس --
it seemed pretty reasonable at the time,
بدا الأمر منطقياً جداً في حينها،
but with each passing year,
لكن مع مرور كل سنة،
I've come to have increasing doubts.
أصبحت لدي شكوك متزايدة.
I've come to understand the sentiments of George Burns,
أصبحت لأفهم وجهة نظر "جورج بيرنز"،
who was performing still in Las Vegas
الذي كان ما يزال يعمل في لاس فيغاس
well into his 90s.
بشكل جسد وهو في التسعين.
And one night, there's a knock at his hotel room door.
في إحدى الليالي، سمع طرقا على باب غرفته في الفندق
He answers the door.
فتح الباب.
Standing before him is a gorgeous, scantily clad showgirl.
وقفت أمامه فتاة استعراض رائعة شبه عارية.
She looks at him and says,
نظرت إليه وقالت،
"I'm here for super sex."
"أنا هنا من أجل جنس هائل."
"That's fine," says George, "I'll take the soup."
قال جورج: "هذا جيد، سآخذ الحساء"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I came to realize,
أصبحت أدرك
as a physician,
كوني طبيباً
that I was working toward a goal
بأنني كنت أعمل في إتجاه هدف
which was different from the goal of evolution --
يختلف عن هدف التطور --
not necessarily contradictory, just different.
ليس بالضرورة أنه يعاكسه، يختلف عنه فقط.
I was trying to preserve the body.
كنت أحاول الحفاظ على الجسد.
I wanted to keep us healthy.
أردت أن نحافظ على صحتنا.
I wanted to restore health from disease.
أردت أن نستعيد الصحة من المرض.
I wanted us to live long and healthy lives.
أردت أن نعيش حياة صحية وطويلة.
Evolution is all about passing on the genome
التطور معني بتمرير الجينات
to the next generation,
للجيل التالي،
adapting and surviving
التأقلم والنجاة
through generation after generation.
جيلاً بعد جيل.
From an evolutionary point of view,
من وجة نظر التطور،
you and I are like the booster rockets
أنت وأنا مثل الصواريخ الدافعة
designed to send the genetic payload
صممت لترسل الحمولة الجينية
into the next level of orbit
إلى المستوى التالي في المدار
and then drop off into the sea.
وبعد ذلك تسقط في البحر.
I think we would all understand the sentiment that Woody Allen expressed
أعتقد بأننا جميعاً نفهم وجهة نظر "وودي آلن"
when he said, "I don't want to achieve immortality through my work.
عندما قال: "أنا لا أريد تحقيق الخلود من خلال عملي.
I want to achieve it through not dying."
أريد تحقيقه بألا أموت"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Evolution does not necessarily
التطور لا يفضل بالضرورة
favor the longest-lived.
صاحب الحياة الأطول.
It doesn't necessarily favor the biggest
إنه لا يفضل بالضرورة الأكبر
or the strongest or the fastest,
أو الأصغر أو الأسرع،
and not even the smartest.
أو حتى الأصغر.
Evolution favors
التطور يفضل
those creatures best adapted
الكائنات ذات التأقلم الأفضل
to their environment.
مع بيئتها.
That is the sole test
هذا هو المعيار الوحيد
of survival and success.
للنجاة والنجاح.
At the bottom of the ocean,
في أعماق المحيط،
bacteria that are thermophilic
بكتيريا تنمو في الحرارة العالية
and can survive at the steam vent heat
ويمكنها النجاه في حرارة نافورة البخار
that would otherwise produce, if fish were there,
والتي تؤدي عكس ذلك، إذا كان تواجد السمك
sous-vide cooked fish,
لعمل سمك مطبوخ بالضغط
nevertheless, have managed
وعلى الرغم من ذلك، فإنها تمكنت
to make that a hospitable environment for them.
من جعل هذا بيئة مضيفة لها.
So what does this mean,
إذن ماذا يعني هذا،
as we look back at what has happened in evolution,
عندما ننظر للوراء إلى الذي حدث في التطور
and as we think about the place again
وعندما نفكر مجدداً في موقع
of humans in evolution,
البشرية في التطور،
and particularly as we look ahead
وبالتحديد عندما ننظر للأمام
to the next phase,
إلى المرحلة التالية،
I would say
يمكنني القول
that there are a number of possibilities.
بأن هنالك عدداً من الاحتمالات.
The first is that we will not evolve.
الأول بأننا لن نتطور.
We have reached
لقد وصلنا إلى
a kind of equipoise.
نوع من التوزان.
And the reasoning behind that would be,
والمسبب في ذلك يكون،
first, we have, through medicine,
أولاً، تمكنا من خلال الأدوية،
managed to preserve a lot of genes
الحفاظ على الكثير من الجينات
that would otherwise be selected out
التي ربما لولا ذلك كانت سوف تستبعد
and be removed from the population.
ويتم إزالتها من المجموع.
And secondly, we as a species
وثانياً، نحن كأجناس
have so configured our environment
لدينا بيئة معدلة كثيراً
that we have managed to make it adapt to us
بحيث أننا جعلناها تتلائم معنا
as well as we adapt to it.
أيضا نحن نتلائم معها.
And by the way, we immigrate and circulate
وبالمناسبة، فإننا نهاجر ونتجول
and intermix so much
ونتمازج كثيراً
that you can't any longer
بحيث أنه لم يعد بإمكانك
have the isolation that is necessary
الحصول على العزلة الضرورية
for evolution to take place.
لحدوث التطور.
A second possibility
الإحتمال الثاني
is that there will be evolution of the traditional kind,
بأنه سيكون هنالك تطور من النوع التقليدي،
natural, imposed by the forces of nature.
طبيعي، تفرضه قوى الطبيعة.
And the argument here would be
والمقولة هنا هي بأنه
that the wheels of evolution grind slowly,
عجلة التطور تدور ببطئ
but they are inexorable.
لكن من دون هوادة.
And as far as isolation goes,
بقدر ما انتهت العزلة،
when we as a species
عندما سنقوم كأجناس
do colonize distant planets,
بالاستعمار في كواكب بعيدة،
there will be the isolation and the environmental changes
ستكون هنالك العزلة وتغييرات البئية المناسبين
that could produce evolution
التي ربما تؤدي للتطور
in the natural way.
بالطريقة الطبيعية.
But there's a third possibility,
لكن هنالك احتمال ثالث،
an enticing, intriguing and frightening possibility.
احتمال جذاب مثير للفضول والخوف.
I call it neo-evolution --
أنا أسميه التطور الجيني "نيو-إيفولوشن"
the new evolution
التطور الجديد
that is not simply natural,
إنه ليس تطوراً بسيطاً.
but guided and chosen
لكنه مختار و موجه
by us as individuals
من قبلنا نحن كأفراد
in the choices that we will make.
بخيارات نختارها نحن.
Now how could this come about?
كيف سيحدث هذا؟
How could it be possible that we would do this?
كيف يمكن أن نستطيع فعل هذا؟
Consider, first, the reality
لنعلم أولا حقيقة
that people today, in some cultures,
بأن الناس اليوم، في بعض الثقافات،
are making choices about their offspring.
يختارون أنسالهم.
They're, in some cultures,
إنهم ، في بعض الثقافات،
choosing to have more males than females.
يختارون إنجاب ذكور أكثر من النساء.
It's not necessarily good for the society,
ليس بالضرورة أن يكون أفضل للمجتمع،
but it's what the individual and the family are choosing.
لكنه ما يختاره الفرد والعائلة.
Think also,
فكر أيضاً،
if it were possible ever
إذا كان بمقدورك يوماً ما
for you to choose, not simply to choose the sex of your child,
أن تختار، ليس جنس طفلك ببساطة فقط
but for you in your body
لكن لك في جسمك
to make the genetic adjustments
أن تقوم بتعديلات جينية
that would cure or prevent diseases.
التي قد تعالج أو تمنع الأمراض.
What if you could make the genetic changes
ماذا لو كنت تستطيع عمل تغييرات جينية
to eliminate diabetes or Alzheimer's
للتخلص من السكري و الألزهايمر
or reduce the risk of cancer
أو تقليل خطر السرطان
or eliminate stroke?
أو التخلص من السكتة ؟
Wouldn't you want
ألن ترغب
to make those changes
بعمل تلك التغييرات
in your genes?
في جيناتك؟
If we look ahead,
لو تطلعنا للأمام،
these kind of changes
لهذا النوع من التغييرات
are going to be increasingly possible.
ستصبح أكثر إمكانية بشكل متزايد.
The Human Genome Project
إن مشروع الجينوم البشري
started in 1990,
بدأ في 1990،
and it took 13 years.
واستغرق 13 سنة.
It cost 2.7 billion dollars.
كلف المشروع 2.7 بليون دولار.
The year after it was finished in 2004,
بعد انتهاءه بسنة في 2004،
you could do the same job
يمكنك إنجاز نفس العمل
for 20 million dollars in three to four months.
لقاء 20 مليون دولار خلال ثلاثة أو أربعة أشهر.
Today, you can have a complete sequence
اليوم، يمكنك الحصول على سلسلة كاملة
of the three billion base pairs in the human genome
للثلاثة بليون زوجاً أساسياً من الجينومات البشرية
at a cost of about 20,000 dollars
بكلفة 20 ألف دولار تقريباً
and in the space of about a week.
وفي غضون أسبوع تقريباً.
It won't be very long
لن يطول الأمر
before the reality will be
قبل أن يصبح واقعاً
the 1,000-dollar human genome,
الجينوم البشري بقيمة ألف دولار،
and it will be increasingly available for everyone.
و بالتدريج المتزايد سيكون متاحاً للجميع.
Just a week ago,
قبل أسبوع واحد فقط،
the National Academy of Engineering
قدمت الأكادمية الوطنية للهندسة
awarded its Draper Prize
جائزتها "درابر برايز"
to Francis Arnold and Willem Stemmer,
لكل من "فرانسيس أرنولد" و"ويليم ستيمر"
two scientists who independently developed techniques
عالمان قاما بشكل مستقل بتطوير تقنيات
to encourage the natural process of evolution to work faster
لتشجيع العملية الطبيعية للتطور لتعمل بسرعة أكبر
and to lead to desirable proteins
و لتؤدي إلى بروتينات مرغوبة
in a more efficient way --
بطريقة أكثر فعالية --
what Frances Arnold calls "directed evolution."
ما دعاه "فرانسيس أرنولد" بـ"التطوير الموجه".
A couple of years ago, the Lasker Prize
قبل عامين، قدمت جائرة "لاسكر برايز"
was awarded to the scientist Shinya Yamanaka
للعالم "شنيا يماناكا"
for his research
من أجل بحثه
in which he took an adult skin cell,
الذي قام فيه بأخذ خلية جلد بالغة،
a fibroblast,
خلية ليفية ،
and by manipulating just four genes,
ومن خلال التعديل في أربعة جينات فقط،
he induced that cell
قام بتحريض تلك الخلية
to revert to a pluripotential stem cell --
لتعود خلية جذعية جنينة (pluripotential) --
a cell potentially capable
خلية بامكانها
of becoming any cell in your body.
أن تصبح أي خلية في جسمك.
These changes are coming.
هذه التغيرات قادمة.
The same technology
نفس التقنية
that has produced the human insulin in bacteria
التي أنتجت الإنسولين البشري في البكتيريا
can make viruses
يمكنها إنتاج فيروسات
that will not only protect you against themselves,
لن تحميك فقط ضدها،
but induce immunity against other viruses.
لكنها تحرض المناعة ضد فيروسات أخرى.
Believe it or not,
صدق أو لا تصدق،
there's an experimental trial going on
بأن هنالك محاولة مخبرية جارية
with vaccine against influenza
للقاح ضد الانفلونزا
that has been grown in the cells of a tobacco plant.
التي كانت تنمو في خلايا نبات التبغ.
Can you imagine something good coming out of tobacco?
هل بإمكانك تخيل أمر جيد يأتي من نبتة التبغ؟
These are all reality today,
هذه كلها حقائق اليوم،
and [in] the future, will be evermore possible.
وفي المستقبل ، ستكون ممكنة أكثر مما سبق.
Imagine then
تخيل بأن
just two other little changes.
تغييران آخران صغيران فقط.
You can change the cells in your body,
يمكنك تغيير خلايا جسمك،
but what if you could change the cells in your offspring?
لكن ماذا لو كنت تستطيع تغيير الخلايا في نسلك ؟
What if you could change the sperm and the ova,
ماذا لو كنت تستطيع تغيير النطاف و البويضة
or change the newly fertilized egg,
أو تغيير البيضة الملحقة حديثاً،
and give your offspring a better chance
و أن تعطي نسلك فرصأ أفضل
at a healthier life --
بحياة أكثر صحة --
eliminate the diabetes, eliminate the hemophilia,
التخلص من السكر ، التخلص من أمراض الدم،
reduce the risk of cancer?
تقليل خطر السرطان ؟
Who doesn't want healthier children?
من لا يريد أطفال أكثر صحة ؟
And then, that same analytic technology,
و عندها ، باستخدام نفس التقنية التحليلية ،
that same engine of science
نفس المحرك العلمي ذلك
that can produce
الذي يستطيع إنتاج
the changes to prevent disease,
تغييرات للتخلص من الأمراض،
will also enable us
سوف يمكننا أيضاً
to adopt super-attributes,
من الحصول على مواصفات خارقة،
hyper-capacities --
إمكانيات عالية للغاية --
that better memory.
ذاكرة أفضل.
Why not have the quick wit
لماذا لا يكون لدينا سرعة البديهة
of a Ken Jennings,
مثل "كين جينينغز"
especially if you can augment it
بشكل خاص إذا كنت تستطيع دعمها
with the next generation of the Watson machine?
بالجيل القادم للكمبيوتر "واطسون"
Why not have the quick twitch muscle
لم لا نمتلك العضلات سريعة التجاوب
that will enable you to run faster and longer?
التي تمكننا من الركض أسرع ولمدة أطول ؟
Why not live longer?
لم لا نعيش مدة أطول ؟
These will be irresistible.
ستكون هذه لا تقاوم .
And when we are at a position
وعندما نكون في موقع
where we can pass it on to the next generation,
بحيث يمكننا تمريرها للأجيال القادمة
and we can adopt the attributes we want,
و يمكننا الحصول على المواصفات التي نرغب بها،
we will have converted
سنكون قد حولنا
old-style evolution
التطوير ذو النمط القديم
into neo-evolution.
إلى التطور الجيني.
We'll take a process
سنأخذ عملية
that normally might require 100,000 years,
تتطلب في العادة مئة ألف سنة،
and we can compress it down to a thousand years --
ويمكننا أن نضغطها إلى ألف سنة --
and maybe even in the next 100 years.
أو حتى ربما في المئة عام المقبلة.
These are choices
هذه هي الخيارات
that your grandchildren,
بالنسبة لأحفادكم
or their grandchildren,
أو أحفادهم
are going to have before them.
ستكون مطروحة أمامهم.
Will we use these choices
هل سنتستخدم هذه الخيارات
to make a society that is better,
لجعل المجتع أفضل،
that is more successful, that is kinder?
ليكون أكثر نجاحاً ، أكثر لطفاً ؟
Or, will we selectively choose different attributes
أو ، سنقوم بشكل انتقائي باختيار المميزات
that we want for some of us
التي نريدها للبعض منا
and not for others of us?
و ليس للبعض الآخر ؟
Will we make a society
هل سنجعل المجتمع
that is more boring and more uniform,
مملاً أكثر و متماثلاً أكثر
or more robust and more versatile?
أم أكثر قوة و أكثر تنوعا ؟
These are the kinds of questions
هذا هو النوع من الأسئلة
that we will have to face.
التي سوف نواجهها.
And most profoundly of all,
و السؤال الأكثر عمقاً على الاطلاق،
will we ever be able to develop the wisdom,
هل سنكون أبدا قادرين على أن نطور الحكمة،
and to inherit the wisdom,
و أن نورث الحكمة ،
that we'll need to make these choices wisely?
التي سوف نحتاجها للقيام بهذه الاختيارات بحكمة ؟
For better or worse,
للأفضل أو للأسوأ ،
and sooner than you may think,
و أقرب مما تتصور ،
these choices will be up to us.
هذه الخيارات ستكون متروكة لنا.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)